Hello friends, welcome back to True
Health Tuesday.
Uh I am Maria Jose Hammel and I am so
glad to be back with you again for
another
um presentation
about health and uh I I promise you that
we would be talking about diabetes and
pre-diabetes and actually as you could
see on the screen other metabolic
diseases and um that's where we will be
beginning today because actually we will
be doing four of these presentations,
maybe even five if we for some reason
are not able to cover everything on uh
on all these you know four Tuesdays that
we will be doing. It won't be four
Tuesdays in a row as you know we do
every other Tuesday. So it was going to
take us about eight weeks to cover this.
It we might go on a to a fifth
presentation just if we are not able to
cover everything. But I just want to
make sure that I give you all the
information that I have because I've
been studying diabetes for so long. I
have all this information in my head
that I want to share with you. So I want
to make sure that you have it. I don't
want to forget to pray. So we're going
to go ahead and pray first. Okay. So
let's start with a prayer. Dear heavenly
father, thank you so much for the
opportunity to be together to have this
wonderful uh technology that allows us
to share this presentation with people
all over the world. And we ask you to be
with us to bless this presentation that
everything that we share together that
may be blessed by you and that may be
for the benefit of everybody who is
connected in Jesus name we pray. Amen.
I want to let you know that I have been
studying diabetes for a long long time.
So, uh it's not something new for me. In
fact, it's one of my, as I guess you
would say, my one of my specialties.
Uh so, I am super excited to share this
with you. In fact, I have this same uh
sort of series in Spanish and I've had
it for a long long time in my YouTube
channel in Spanish. And this is the
first time this is going to be like uh
in English on YouTube. So I'm super
happy that this is going to be, you
know, uh published in uh in this in
these YouTube channels. So super happy
about that. I just want to get started
with the disclaimer that I always give
that this is not meant to be any kind of
treatment for anybody. So I don't want
anybody to think that this is going to
be, you know, somehow you uh some some
kind of prescription for anyone. It's
not. It's just meant to be educational.
number one. Number two, as you always
know, I always go by the uh spiritual
rule that I always follow, which is to
the law and the testimony as Isaiah 8:20
says, I hope you follow that as well.
And I also wanted to let you know uh
aside from the spiritual guideline that
I always follow for not always not only
not only my spiritual uh teachings as if
you will but also for nutrition and
health. I also follow this to the law
and the testimony. But I also believe in
the importance of scientific
um scientific knowledge. And as you see
at the bottom, opinion, experts opinion
is kind of the lowest quality of uh of
scientific
um evidence if you will. At the top you
see reviews, metaanalysis. That's the
highest quality of scientific evidence.
And if if you wanted to know why I think
that this is so important, this is from
Christian education. The top uh
quotation says, "An knowledge of scient
of science of all kinds is power and it
is the purpose of God that advanced
science shall be taught in our schools
as a preparation for the work that is to
precede the closing scenes of earth's
history." That's right now, right now,
right now. I think so closely is health
related to our happiness that we cannot
have the latter without the former. A
practical knowledge of science of all of
human life is necessary in order to
glorify God in our bodies. So that is
why I think scientific knowledge is so
important and to follow scientific
evidence is so important.
And God wants us to have common sense.
He wants us to reason from common sense.
I just wanted to also share that with
you. I always share this with everyone
but I just wanted to be at the beginning
of every one of my presentations because
not always uh people who have seen my
previous presentations or you know
people who are connected today have seen
my previous presentations. I just wanted
to always share that. But to begin
today, I want you to I wanted to share
with you why um why you know my
background is when it comes to diabetes.
About 15 years ago, I started working at
a clinic in Watsonville. And uh this is
it. Well, it doesn't look like this
anymore. Uh but this is Salutarente and
it's a clinic, a community clinic in
Watsonville, California. It's been
remodeled so it looks a little different
right now. But I was a um I was a
clinical nutritionist for five and a
half years and I worked with uh with
diabetics a lot. In fact, I worked in
the women's health area. So I worked
with a lot of gestational diabetics but
type two diabetes as well uh for many
years. So that's one thing that I did
for many many years. But also I wanted
to show you the fellowship hall of the
Wattsville 7th Day Adventist Church. And
I was a member for many many years until
transfer of my membership to living
mana. So right before I transfer my
membership to living mana uh online
church, I was a member to of the
Watsonville 7th Adventist Church and for
about 10 years we did a reversing
diabetes um uh seminar and it lasted for
six weeks every year in the fall and uh
we invited members of the community.
Most of the people who came to our
seminar were non Adventist. Between 20
to 30 people came every year. We used to
do it two times a year in the beginning
and then we had to move to once a year
only because of my work. Actually I was
too busy to do it twice a year but we
used to get about 20 25 to 30 people
every year. Most of them are
non-adventists
uh who would come. So by the way health
could be actually used for evangelism. I
think I've said this many times, but
health is evangelism.
FYI, I hope you're listening. I hope
you're paying attention to what I'm
saying. Health is evangelism. Uh so all
these people from the communities to
come to our classes about six weeks on
how to reverse not only diabetes but
obviously pre-diabetes and all the
related conditions that we talked about
the first day. If you haven't seen the
first presentation that I gave for True
Health Tuesdays, it's called 10 Days to
Better Health. I hope you're watch it if
you haven't seen it. I will talk a
little bit about that
uh here because it's a little bit
related to what we're going to talk
about today. But yes, a blessing for the
community. You can do this too, by the
way. If you want to work with your local
church, you can do this. Uh you can take
any of my uh slides and use them to give
presentations at your local church.
So anyway, that's what we did for about
10 years. We did also some food demos as
part of this. Um and uh anyway, so
that's what we I did too. This is a
picture of me um translating from Dr. M.
Milton Tesy. Mil Dr. Milton Tesky worked
for Weimar Institute and Weimar
Institute is right here in uh in
California. It's uh owned by 7th Day
Adventist and they have a program called
New Start. I don't know how many of you
have heard of New Start. Put a one in
the chat or put me or put something in
the chat if you heard of the New Start
program. New start, the letters, the
eight letters of New Start represent the
eight principles of health taught by the
Seventh Day Adventist Church
as taught by Yes, one. Okay, we have a
one already. Yes, thank you, Harriet.
uh as taught the eight principles of
health as taught by the seven church
given to us by the um by the uh spirit
of prophecy. We have another one. Yes.
Uh so new um the Weimar Institute uses
these eight principles of health to for
a for a program they actually use people
come and stay for I think two weeks. I
don't remember exactly, but a lot of
people come there with their chronic
conditions and they stay there. Well,
Dr. Tesy worked for them actually giving
giving these um seminars at churches
during the weekends. He would do this
for many many years. I went with him to
Honduras and I translated his
presentations. Uh I went as a
nutritionist as well. So, I gave some of
the nutrition presentations. There was
another nutritionist who went with us
who gave the uh cooking demos. I
translated for her but I translated his
medical presentations. I learned a lot
from him. I incorporated that knowledge
into my presentations. This was many
years ago about seven or eight years
ago. And so I learned from him from the
wear you know that he had. So I
incorporated that into my knowledge. By
the way we went there we did a six-day
seminar. We invited people from the
community. This was in rural Honduras,
you guys. I thought in Honduras for No,
there for sure, for sure. For sure.
People in rural Honduras would
definitely not have all these conditions
that people here in the United States
have. You know, people live in the
country over there and, you know, grow
their own food. Oh, we have another one.
Yes. Um, I thought for sure people in
rural Honduras would not have diabetes,
high, you know, high cholesterol, high
blood pressure, all these chronic
conditions. Boy, was I wrong. Even
though people live in the country and
very natural settings over there, grow
their own food, they have the same
things, you guys. Diabetes, high
cholesterol, high blood pressure, high
weight. And so, we did the exact uh same
things we teach over here. We taught
people how to exercise, how to eat
better. We would take their uh blood
blood glucose in the morning before they
ate breakfast. Then we took them for
walks. Then we did presentations. We
gave them, you know, good food,
plant-based. Like I said, I uh did some
of the translation. Here's the other
nutritionist from the Fresno 7 Adventist
Church. And I translated for her. So
anyway, I learned a lot from these
people and that's how I learned a lot of
the knowledge that I'll share I'll share
today. And then as I said the first
presentation that I gave 10 days to
better health today I work for a
nonprofit and we do a program called
community RX in English. The day the
name in Spanish is saludent to plateau
which is a 10-day program we do for the
community and we help people to first of
all eat a whole food plant-based diet
for 10 days and we help people to
improve their health and we only have
them for 10 days. We teach them how to
uh eat a plant-based diet. We can't go
check what they're actually eating. We
only rely on what they tell us. But I
just wanted to show you real quick. I
don't know if I actually showed you some
of the results. I might not have had the
time to show you on that first
presentation some of the actual results
from people. I don't remember actually
if I showed you or not. I just wanted to
show you just some results. It's not
that everybody gets the same results,
but the these are some success stories.
Okay, these are not the real names
obviously for privacy um uh reasons, but
I just wanted to I I did put in bold uh
some of the uh some of the results that
have to do with diabetes just so that
you see uh because we're talking about
diabetes today, but actually you you can
see even some of the cholesterol numbers
how much they changed in only well two
weeks because we do this on Sundays. So
there's two Sundays, three Sundays
actually. So they come after 14 days.
But in 14 days, these are some of the
numbers, you guys. For instance, this
lady, her fasting glucose went down from
158 to 71. Somebody's cholesterol went
down from 228 to 148. This is high from
from super nice, right? Like this is
statins. You get they give you statins
and this is no statins needed, right?
LDL, this is very very high. This is
wonderful. No statins needed right here.
Okay, so this is amazing results.
There's like no medication that will
give you this kind of results in two
weeks. Look at this person's fasting
glucose. This is definitely in the di
This is diabetic for sure. They'll give
you like
for sure metformin with this kind of
numbers. Maybe even insulin. I don't
know. Like 184 is definitely diabetic.
Uh look at these triglycerides number.
Oh, by the way, this person went from
184 to 74. Now, if they stay with this
diet, it's very likely that they will
remain with these numbers. If they go
back to eating what they were eating
before, it's possible they'll go back to
really bad numbers. But if they if they
persevere, it's very likely that they
will uh keep the good numbers. Look at
these persons triglycerides off the
charts. Uh same here. People will lose
uh weight. I mean, these are amazing
numbers. I don't have a lot of time to
go over but look at these fasting
glucose numbers okay I mean these are
the percentages the percentages look at
the percentages okay this is only in 10
days LDL drop 22% 25% 27% 30% 38% 51%
these are the kinds of numbers we see
when people eat a whole food plant-based
n uh diet and this is just the diet we
don't even tell them to exercise we
don't have the ability to really do an
intense lifestyle program. But at
Weimar, that's what they do. Okay.
That's what they do. Intense lifestyle.
They cover everything. We only do the
diets. This is the kind of things that
you do. Are you a member of American
Lifestyle? Oh, thank you. Because I was
just going to show you that today I got
an email. This is just very timely. I
It's not I I don't want to brag. It's
not that I want to brag. I just want to
I just wanted to let you know that I'm
not making things up that when I tell
you these things, you can trust that
this is good quality information. I just
got an email from uh from the American
Life uh College of Lifestyle Medicine. I
am a member, yes, but I got an email
today that I finally got my my
certification
for uh be that I I I submitted all my
paperwork like weeks ago. I am a member.
I'm also certified as a lifestyle uh
medicine professional, but I finally got
my also my other certification which is
a certification for type 2 diabetes
remission. So I have two certifications
from the American American College of
Lifestyle Medicine. I have the
certification from for being a lifestyle
medicine professional. That's like the
basic certification, but this is an
additional certification for type two
diabetes remission because I took the
additional classes for uh for for
diabetes remission. Type two diabetes
remission. I just got this email today.
So, I just wanted to share this with
you. I'm super happy that I got this
certification as well. So, so this is
very timely. Super duper. So, Pamela,
you're also Yay. Also super duper. Yeah,
this is this is a great um this is a
great organization and one of the things
that I really was very ingrained in my
brain after I got certified is the
importance of evidence of being
evidence-based and I I really appreciate
that from the training uh uh yeah thank
you thank you Pamela uh from from the
training from American College of
Medicine which by the way is an
organization that was started by
Adventist doctors it's now expanded way
beyond that But uh but yeah, it's it's a
very great organization. I really like
it. Anyway, I wanted to then move on and
let's talk about uh why are diabetes and
other chronic diseases so common and
what why are they related? We're going
to talk about that too. But there, as
you know, there's different types of
diabetes. Diabetes type two is the most
common one. 90 to 95% of diabetics are
type two diabetics. But it's not the
only kind of diabetes. As you probably
know,
there's type one, which is actually an
autoimmune disease. It's not as common
as type one. Type uh as type two, sorry.
Type two is the most common. Type one is
much less common. Is an autoimmune
disease.
It used to be called juvenile diabetes.
Did you know this? It's no longer called
juvenile diabetes. Do you know why type
1 diabetes is no longer called juvenile
diabetes?
It's the kind of diabetes that happens
because
the cells in the pancreas that are in
charge of producing insulin in the
pancreas are completely destroyed
uh by this autoimmune
um process that happens. In other words,
your own immune system destroys these
cells that produce insulin, but the this
usually happens in childhood and so it's
usually diagnosed in childhood and by
default you absolutely have to take
insulin for the rest of your life.
It used to be called uh um juvenile
diabetes because it's always
diagnosed in youth in in childhood, but
it's no longer called that way. And by
the way, type two diabetes used to be
called adult onset diabetes. So that's
the differentiation. It used to be that
type two was always diagnosed
40 year plus, you know, always. And the
reason why this one is no no longer
called juvenile and the type two is no
longer called adult onset is because
type 2 diabetes is now diagnosed also in
children. In fact, when I was working at
Salutarente, the community clinic in
Watsonville, California,
the youngest person that I saw with my
own eyes, now this is my own personal
experience, and there's probably much
younger children that have been
diagnosed. This is just in my own
personal experience. The youngest person
that I saw with my own eyes in my office
with type 2 diabetes already diagnosed
and taking medications for type 2
diabetes was 12 years old. A young girl
with type 2. I'm only 5, you guys. I'm
very short. She was 510,
12 years old.
510 220 pounds at 12
12 years old. So, and that's only the
youngest person I have seen. There's
probably younger children with type two.
Therefore, type two is no longer adult
onset.
So, type one cannot just be called
juvenile because guess what? Type two is
also juvenile if you if you will if it
happens at young ages. So those terms
are no longer used. Okay. So that's type
one. It's an autoimmune disease.
Type one. Type two is not an autoimmune
disease. It's a lifestyle disease.
That's the one we're going to
concentrate a little bit more because
it's related to the other ones that we
have been talking about. uh because it
has to do with insulin resistance which
is what we talked about on the first
presentation when we talked about 10
days to better health.
Um and the body is okay somebody's
talking about the body makes its own
insulin every day. Yes, except for type
one. So it doesn't because then the you
know the autoimmune um the autoimmune
process actually destroys this those um
cells. Okay. There's also gestational
diabetes that I mentioned earlier and uh
it's a little bit related to actually
the lifestyle diabetes in the sense I
don't know how many of you know this but
50% of women
actually there's yeah 50% of women who
have had gestational diabetes go on to
develop type 2 diabetes. Did you know
this? How many of you knew this?
50% of women with gestational uh
diabetes go on to develop type two. And
with Hispanic women, at least I think
most minority women, people of color,
it's within the first five years after
giving birth.
How many of you knew this? So yes, they
are related. They're actually related.
Type two and justational. All right,
there's another one. You guys,
how many have how many of you have heard
of
type
1.5?
I bet you you haven't heard of that or
most of you. How many of you had heard
of 1.5 before today?
1.5.
It's actually the autoimmune. It's
autoimmune diabetes just like diabetes
one, type one, but it happens in adult
age. That's why it's 1.5. It's kind of
in between one and two. So Pamela had
heard of it. That's because she's a
member of ACLM. That's why she heard it.
All right. Great Pamela. Congrats.
Any anybody else have heard of this?
Anyway, it's between one and two because
it's autoimmune, but it happens in adult
life. So, it's latent autoimmune
diabetes in adults. Lada. Interesting,
right?
It could be misdiagnosis type two.
So
you have to be careful if you have
diabetes
and you tried lifestyle modifications
and for some reason that is not
responding to lifestyle modifications.
You could have your doctor check for
antibodies and they could determine
whether you have an autoimmune diabetes
and it could be it could it could be an
autoimmune diabetes. In that case it's
1.5. It's not two. And in that case, you
might need to take
um you might need to take insulin just
if you as if you had type one. But we
will take we will talk about actually
how lifestyle modifications are just as
important for people who have type 1
diabetes,
1.5
to all of the diabetes actually. All
right, one more thing. Have you ever
heard of type
three diabetes?
Anybody?
You're like, "What?" Many of you are
probably like, "You got to be kidding
me. There's no such a thing as type
three diabetes.
Never heard of this."
Well,
well, there's a hint right here, right
on the screen. It says sugar in your
brain. It has to do with the brain. Will
you in the future talk about types of
anemia? Well, that's a good idea. I
could
tell me more about it. What do you want
to hear? All right, I'll tell you what.
Type three. Here it is. Do you see
Alzheimer's disease?
Alzheimer's disease. You can take a
picture of this, read it on your own.
Basically what it says right here is
that insulin resistance, remember when
we talked about insulin resistance, any
of you who watched the first
presentation, 10 days to better health,
we talked about the underlying
reason for diabetes and
pre-diabetes and all the other
conditions related to insulin
resistance.
It could actually happen in the brain,
too. That's what this abstract is
talking about. And if you go on to read
the the whole study, it will it will
tell you basically that insulin
resistance happens in the brain. Happens
in all the whole body obviously. So
that's what it's talking about. Now
if you haven't watched the first
presentation, I highly recommend you go
back and watch it because I won't have
too much time. I don't want to take too
much time talking about the root cause
of type two diabetes and the other
chronic diseases we already covered it
so I don't want to spend too much time
on it but okay my microcystic anemia I
will make a note of that and I will look
into it and thank you for that um for
that suggestion all right I will not
like I said I won't spend too much time
on this because it's already been
covered in that first presentation but
what we talked about in the first
presentation was the fact that we have
glucose as you know is the fuel for the
cells. That fuel needs to go inside of
the cells and it goes into the cells
through these cell through these recep
receptors. These receptors are usually
not open all the time and what opens
these receptors is insulin which acts as
a key. Sometimes is uh illustrated as a
key. I illustrated in my little drawing
here as a stickman. Basically, what the
insulin does is opens up the receptors
for glucose to go inside of the cell
then to be used uh as a fuel. And
actually in this drawing, what you see
right here, these little organels inside
the cell uh that you see with the green
and the little red inside, these
organels inside the cell are called
mitochondria. And the mitochondria is
basically like the little engines or the
furnaces if you will. That's where the
glucose gets converted into energy. It's
kind of like the engines inside of the
cell which actually make the energy for
you to function, for you to move, for
you to wake up, do everything you need
to do. All the cells, everything that
happens in your body needs energy. So
that's where the magic happens in the
mitochondria. So basically the glucose
is the fuel for that. So the insulin
opens it up opens up these channels for
the uh glucose to go in and uh and be
used up as as the fuel. But what's been
happening
uh with the modern lifestyle if you will
sedenturism and excess calories
particularly excess fat in the diet and
accumulation of fat in the body as well
is that we have this m intramiocellular
accumulation of lipids intramyiocellular
lipids we talked about this so if you
haven't heard this I'm just going over
it again but I really covered it in
detail in that first presentation 10
days to better health. So what we have
is an accumulation of fat
within the cells. This is the
intrammyiocellular.
Intra
means inside. Myo means muscle. Cellular
means cells. So inside of muscle cells
mostly lipids means fat. So we see this
abnormal accumulation of fats within
cells and this abnormal accumulation of
fat within cells produces this uh uh
block this uh interference with the
action of insulin and that is the
basically the um the basis of this
theory of insulin resistance. So the
insulin is there. There is no lack of
insulin at the moment. The insulin is
there but the the action of insulin is
being blocked by the intramiocellular
lipids
and that's why then you see an
accumulation of glucose outside of the
cell. Now the pancreas tries to then
uh do something about this uh this
situation and the only thing that
pancreas can do at the moment is produce
more insulin. This is hyperinsulinemia.
So this is the first problem you start
to see number one hyperglycemia and
number two hyperinsulinemia.
Now we got two problems you see and of
course we have uh too much fat. So now
we have hyper uh lipidmia, right? Hyper
lipids, too many lipids, hyper lipidmia,
hyper glycemia, hyper uh insulinia. Too
many wrong things going on at the same
time. Now the thing is all this insulin
actually is kind of covering up the
problem. We'll see that in a minute, but
it's actually covering up the problem. I
did talk about this last time, too, but
I just wanted to show you other
illustrations. This is more of a
textbook illustration. And you see
normal cell here. And the insulin and
the glucose is going in. The glucose is
these red little balls is actually going
in normally. But the bottom here, this
is an insulin resistant cell. You see
the blocked channels, the insulin
receptors. Well, they're blocked and the
in glucose is not going in. And in this
other illustration here, the yellow
balls that do, you see the yellow balls
right there? That's the
intrammyiocellular lipid. Do you see
that? Intrammyiocellular lipid means
fat, you guys. Fat inside of the cell.
Inside of the cell. That's very
important. Now, here's another
illustration just for you know sake of
more illustration so that you see what
is a healthy
uh healthy process. the top. In type
one, the pancreas is not producing
insulin. That's type one. That's the
middle one. Type two, insulin is being
produced. That's the difference. In type
two, insulin is there. What's not
happening is the insulin working
properly. So that's insulin resistance.
Insulin is there, but it's not working.
All right. Also, last time I showed you,
oh, first before that, I wanted to make
sure that I mentioned that insulin is
being produced in extra amounts. That's
hyperinsulinemia. That's one way you can
actually know if you have insulin
resistance. You can your doctor can
order that test. You can be tested for
hyperinsulinemia. That's one way to know
if you have insulin resistance. Last
time I also showed this table. This
comes from the book Goodbye Diabetes. I
actually recommend this book. It's one
of the first books I read on diabetes
and insulin resistance. It's a great
book from Dr. Wes Youngberg from Lumal
Linda. Highly recommend. I actually met
Dr. Wes Yonberg in person. He's a really
nice person. So this is one table that
is very illustrative of what I'm kind of
trying the point I'm trying to make
because the top row you see fasting
blood sugar
uh all the way to the right you see
diabetes stage five and that's diabetes
that's when your blood sugar at fasting
blood sugar is 126 or more that's
definitely diabetes stage three right
there in the middle see says
pre-diabetes if your blood sugar is 100
or more That's pre-diabetes. Okay, we
all know that. Okay, fine. If your blood
sugar is 100, pre-diabetes, but what uh
Youngberg is right there, right below
the table. That's the last name. You can
see it right below the the table.
Youngberg. That's Youngberg.
Uh but you the the name is spelled right
there, right below the the table.
Uh what but the point I made last time
is that and this is actually in the book
and it's very well explained by Dr.
Youngberg in the book is that if your
blood sugar fasting is above the optimal
and look at optimal all the way in the
left
uh optimal blood sugar is between 70 and
84. All right, but it's below
pre-diabetes that's stage three over
here. So it's 100 and plus. So if you go
tomorrow to doctor, they take out your
fasting blood sugar and it's 90.
What's your doctor going to say?
Your doctor's going to say, "You know
what? Great.
Bravo. Your blood sugar is normal.
Go home. Everything's good. Keep eating
what you're eating. You're doing great.
Bravo."
Right.
Isn't that what they're going to say?
Oh, good.
Dr. Younger says, and actually not, he's
not the only one. This is if you're a
member of ACLM, you're probably going to
hear this over and over again. What's
going on here is that
maybe this is not all good.
It's above optimal below pre-diabetes.
What Dr. Youngberg observed when he went
to Guam, I told you all this story in
the first presentation, go watch it. is
that there's people who have they're
within these two numbers, right? 84 and
100 that are already experiencing the
complications.
We'll talk about those complications are
in a minute that are already
experiencing the complications of high
blood sugar
or actually the complications of insulin
resistance
without having pre-diabetes yet without
having listen to me this is very
important they are already experiencing
the complications
of insulin resistance
before having pre-diabetes
the complications of insulin resistance
because you can have insulin resistance
and have the complications of insulin
resistance before having the
pre-diabetes, before having diabetes.
That's the issue.
Insulin resistance has complications
beyond diabetes, beyond pre-diabetes.
That's why I titled this presentation
reversing diabetes and metabolic
diseases because it's not just about
diabetes and pre-diabetes. It's other
things related.
That's why it's important to know this.
What is insulin resistance and its
complications?
Well, these people were experiencing
those complications way before
they started having pre-diabetes. This
is a process that can last years before
you get to pre-diabetes.
You see what I'm saying? That's why it's
important to know this. Dr. Youngerberg
observed these people. They were young.
Why were they having high blood
pressure, fatty liver, and high lipids,
and all these other things, and high
triglycerides, and why? They were young.
Why were they having these things? Well,
because they were insulin resistant.
So then he actually u published another
one later. This other table much more
expanded. And at the bottom, do you see
the bottom row? It says increase heart
disease risk. Do you see that the
bottom?
That's why this is important to know
because you start experiencing increased
heart disease risk way before you get to
pre-diabetes.
Way before diabetes for sure.
You don't have to have diabetes to have
increased heart disease risk.
You don't even have to have
pre-diabetes.
Look at this table.
You already have 20% increased heart
disease risk. You don't even have
pre-diabetes yet.
No pre-diabetes yet. Your doctor will
say your
blood sugar is normal at 95. You already
have high higher risk of heart disease.
See
why? Because there's insulin resistance.
Now, I also showed you this last time. I
don't know if you remember it. These are
the complications. Do you see how many?
Here's type one. Here's type one and a
half. Do you see the top? Type one, then
type one and a half. We already talked
about this. Pre-diabetes, type two,
gestational. Okay, that's all the
diabetes we talked about. Then on the
right after gestational
there's cancer.
What's cancer have to do with all this?
High blood sugar is a high risk for
cancer. You guys,
it is
coronary artery disease. We already know
that. Did you know that 70% of diabetics
don't die of diabetes? They die of
either a heart attack or stroke. 70% of
diabetics die of either a heart attack
or stroke,
hypertension,
atherosclerosis, obesity, high
cholesterol, fatty liver,
PCOS.
What's that have to do with anything?
Yes, insulin resistance related to PCOS.
Alzheimer's, I just mentioned that. Type
three diabetes. What? Yes.
Neuropathy. Well, we already know that
diabetics have that. Blindness. Yes.
Your retina, which is up up above, says
retinopathy,
your retina detaches
and you become blind. I met someone at
40 years old right here in Watsonville,
20 minutes from where I live. 40 year
old lady, young woman. 40 years old is
super young. Don't you think? 40 years
old, completely blind.
completely blind from diabetes.
So, neuropathy,
uh, blindness, kidney failure. How many
people have I met that have diialysis? I
can't even tell you.
You know, getting diialysis because of
diabetes.
Do you know how much it lowers the
quality of life
to have to go to some dialysis center
three or four times a week, be hooked up
to a machine for hours? You know what
that diialysis machine does? It takes
all your blood out, filters it because
that's what your kidneys are. They're
filters. They'll filter the poison in
your blood, put it in the pee, and
basically flush it out of your body. And
when your kidneys don't work, you poison
yourself, right? You don't flush out all
the poisons, so you start poisoning
yourself. So, you have to be hooked into
a machine that will filter those poisons
out of your toxins out of your body so
you don't poison yourself. That's what
the That's what diialysis is. So, kidney
failure, retinopathy, and erectile
dysfunction. All of these things are
related
to insulin resistance. You can have all
of these things or these things that are
not diabetes of course before diabetes.
That's why it's so important. That's why
it's so important to know about these
things. We talked about the liver. Fatty
liver is an insulin resistant liver.
And you could have high cholesterol. I
already said high cholesterol, high
glucose, high fatty acids. So high
hyperc cholesterolmia, hypoglycemia,
hyper lipidmia.
And this high cholesterol will spill out
into the rest of your body and travel
through these arteries. This high
cholesterol will travel through these
arteries and start to accumulate
inside of the arteries. And guess what?
That will then lead to atherosclerosis.
Then we will you know LDL
concentrations, arterial plaque,
hypertension. you will need statins and
of course it will lead to higher
mortality
all these uh diseases. So what again are
the reasons be for this is the fat
and so people confuse this right people
confuse they think it's all the sugar
it's not just all the sugar the sugar
just turns into fat that's why sugar is
a problem because it turns into fat but
people forget that fat is already fat it
doesn't have to be turned into fat
fat is already fat and consuming too
much fat is just as much of a problem
and fat is a bigger problem
and of course lack of exercise because
if we were running marathons every day
then it would be no problem.
You see now look at this interesting uh
interesting uh slides slide you can
actually have an auto. So this is what I
was talking about how
eating a healthy diet and lifestyle
is important for both type one and type
two because a as a type 1 diabetic a
person can actually have
unhealthy lifestyle let's say and so
they can have the autoimmune diabetes
with an unhealthy lifestyle they can
actually start developing insulin
resistance as well. Let's say they eat a
highfat diet, which a lot of people with
type one, they're told to eat a low carb
diet. So, they start eating a low carb
diet, meaning usually high fat, high
protein, high fat. They might be
sedentary. So, now they start developing
insulin resistance. So, they have the
type one and they have insulin
resistance. Now, they have what some
people call double diabetes. Have you
ever heard of that before?
Double diabetes.
What?
It's a new concept. New concept for some
people. Double diabetes. Type one and
type two
because you got the autoimmune and the
insulin resistance
both.
That's why lifestyle modifications are
just as important for type one. and one
and a half and two both of everyone
justational
everybody will benefit from lifestyle
modifications isn't that interesting now
here's where the confusion comes I ask
people what's elevates blood sugar more
eating high carb or high fat
what do you think
what in a okay in a person who's not
diabetic Okay,
a person who's not diabetic,
what will elevate blood sugar more? Put
it in the chat. Eating a highfat meal or
eating a high carb meal.
What will elevate blood sugar more? What
do you think? Because most people get it
wrong.
What do you think?
put it in the chat.
I don't see anybody. High fat. Okay.
Last time I I did this with a Spanish
group,
I had half and half. Half people said
high carb and the other pe half said
high fat. Huh.
I was like well because I usually get
you know so five years ago I would ask
this question 90% would say hi car
to the other day I did this presentation
last week on Tuesday actually last week
seven days ago with a Spanish oh so far
is four high fats no high carbs so fatoo
high fat is winning so last week seven
days ago I did this presentation and it
was half and half 50%. Highfat 50% high
carb. Today the highfat is winning. I
think I have a very educated group
today. Well you guys congrats
because the highfat one today. So let me
show you this very old study old
where they studied this. Now this is
like I said non-diabetics because a
diabetic we already know they eat a
they're they already are insulin
resistant they cannot tolerate carbs. So
they eat carbs they cannot metabolize
them. But with a person who is
non-diabetic
they divided them in two. They gave them
a high fat high and the other person a
high carb and this is what happened.
Here is the result. The highfat meal.
You're welcome, Aaron. Uh, the highfat
meal elevates the blood sugar more than
the high carb.
But most people, now you guys are highly
educated, you already know the right
answer. But you ask people in the
street, what do you think they're going
to say? I would bet more than 50% of
people will say high carb. In fact, all
the keto people will say high carb. You
know that all the people, all the keto
people have this wrong perception that
is the carbs that are the enemy and the
fat is all the good stuff. Fat is good.
Carbs are bad.
And yet here we have
the science that shows us that fat will
produce
insulin resistance. So, I have a a
video. I only have it in Spanish, you
guys. But there's because there's plenty
of information in English. That's why I
make it in Spanish because in Spanish
there's so little that somebody has to
do it in Spanish. So, I had to do it in
English or I mean how to do it in
Spanish. In English, there's plenty. So,
I had it a Spanish video, but you know
what? in my Spanish channel. That's the
one video that has the most thumbs down
is so unpopular because all the keto
haters, I mean, the keto haters that
hate my video, they love keto, they hate
my video. So, the video is called why
the keto diet is the worst for diabetes.
So, the people who love keto and hate my
video, thumbs down on my video.
And I say that keto diet is the worst
for diabetes. The reason why is because
you start eating high fat, high fat,
high fat. Okay? You're not eating any
carbs. So, of course, you start eating
keto,
you're not eating carbs. Okay? All of a
sudden, your A1C is like on the floor.
Your uh fasting glucose is like boom,
super low. Why? Of course, you're not
eating carbs. What are you going to
convert into glucose? You got no carbs
in your diet. You've got no glucose. So,
of course, your glucose is low. But
you're eating all this fat, all this
fat, all this fat, all this fat. Guess
what's happening? You're making yourself
super insulin resistant. You're making
yourself super carb intolerant.
While you're not eating any carbs, no
problem.
Guess what? Next, after 6 months, guess
what happens? Next time you eat an
apple, you have a piece of bread.
Because what happens to your glucose?
Boom. All of a sudden, you can't eat
bread anymore. You can't metabolize
carbs.
Is that what you want? Not being able to
ever eat normal like a normal person.
Most people stay on keto for 6 months
and then they have they drop because
they can't live like that forever. It's
not sustainable for most people.
Did you know that? Most people can't
live like that. Anyway, so just so you
know, I don't think it I think it's the
worst. I wanted to give you some uh
interesting statistics. I think this is
kind of scary, honestly.
This is just pre-diabetes.
This is not even insulin resistance.
This is pre-diabetes. 100 plus
uh fasting glucose. Half of adults age
40 to 59 have pre-diabetes. Did you know
half
23 of adults 68 60 to 74 and three4s
of adult older than 74 adults older than
74 the first time we did our program
at my work December of 2022 I got hired
in September we did in December 2022 and
my boss said you know we should partner
with a church you know because our
program is based on um it was community
RX is the name in English and we she
started it because of a film there's a
documentary called plant pure nation
made by Nelson Campbell the son of T
Colin Campbell T Colin Campbell is very
famous uh he's luminary in the
plant-based community his son Nelson
made a documentary I think it was 2017
that came
uh called Plure Nation and they go to a
church somewhere in the east coast I
think African-American church I think
and you see in the church the people do
the program 10 days and they do great
blah blah blah and so my boss oh my
goodness I'm running out of time you
guys okay my my boss is like why don't
we partner with a church do you know any
churches and I'm like yeah any Spanish
churches
yeah well do you think they would want
to do a 10day
Yeah, I think they would want to do a
10day program. It's in the Bible. All
right. Well, can you call them? Sure.
Okay. Let We did the 10day program at
the Spanish Watson Church, 7th Day
Adventist.
34 members of the church uh signed up.
92%
high hypertension, didn't know. Over 90%
had pre-diabetes. They did not know.
You see these numbers right here? Most
people have pre-diabetes or hypension.
They don't know.
My goodness. All right. Another
statistic that's super scary.
Do you know that it's predicted that
kids are now they're not even kids
anymore. Kids that were born after 2000,
they're young people now in their 20s.
Of course, some of them are kids. So
anybody who's been born after the year
2000, they expect that onethird will be
diabetic in their life. But this is in
the general population between Hispanics
and African-Americans, it'll be one out
of two. Half
the kids who are people of color
will be diabetic.
My goodness gracious.
So what are the causes? Again, these are
all lifestyle related for the most part
because most people will be type two.
Number one, the fat we carry that's
obesity and overweight, this atapost
tissue
will infiltrate into the cells and will
become also that intramyiocellular
lipid. Okay? So that will block the
action of insulin. Uh and by the way,
you can become you can be a skinny fat
person by the way. So just because
you're normal weight doesn't mean you
don't have atapost tissue. So this is on
the left you see normal body composition
but on the right you see an unhealthy
body composition. You can have normal
weight and still have excess fat. You
can even be normal weight and be obese
if you have unhealthy body composition.
So just because you have normal weight
doesn't mean you're not obese.
You can still have abnormal body
composition. So, make sure you check
your body composition. Even if you're
quote unquote normal, if you're not
doing proper exercise, we're going to
talk about this in our third part of
this four-part series. Don't miss it.
It's very important. By the way, this is
in uh I have a quote of the spirit of
prophecy that talks about this. You
don't want to miss that. Presentations
number three. We're number one. So, be
in six weeks or four weeks. I don't even
know how to count anymore, but don't
miss that one. Number three. All right.
Uh, two. Number two cause rich diet.
Eating excess fat. That fat does not
need to be converted into fat. The sugar
will be converted to fat. By the way,
fructose is not used like glucose as
fuel for the cells. Glucose is used as
fuel for the cells. fructose.
Industrialized fructose. Fruit fructose
from fruit does not get does not do this
because it has fiber. But industrialized
fructose does not have fiber. It goes
straight to the liver and it becomes
fat.
FYI, fat is already fat. Does not need
to be converted. It goes
straight
to our cells, to our liver, everywhere.
All right. No bueno.
Okay,
next. Lack of exercise. Because if
you're running all the time, if you're
exercising, if you're moving your body,
well, you can eat a little bit more
calories. Also, of course, you want to
be eat a healthy calorie. But if you're
also not using your body, well, like I
said, we're going to talk about that in
our third presentation.
Genetics. Most people say, a lot of
people say anyway, well, you know, I
have diabetes because my mom, my my dad,
my grandma, everybody in my family
diabetes, so I inherited the diabetes,
so it's not my fault. Really?
Well, you're partly right.
Well, not exactly. You actually uh have
a predisposition if you have a family
member, especially direct family member
with diabetes. Yes, you do have that
predisposition, but that's not the whole
story.
You still have to activate those genes.
Those genes can be deactivated. That's
epigenetics. You can you need to
activate those genes. If they're not
activated, you're not going to get the
diabetes or pre-di or you know,
pre-diabetes or whatever other chronic
disease. Very closely related to this is
ethnic origin. When I used to work at
the clinic, every single woman that we
had in our clinic that was pregnant, we
had to test for diabetes because every
single woman was minority. And being
part of a minority group automatically
put them at a high risk for diabetes,
just being ethnic minority. But guess
what? I'm gonna just tell you a story.
In the United States, the ethnic group
with the highest
rate of diabetes. Do you know which
group it is, by the way? What group do
you think? Ethnic group the highest rate
of diabetes in the United States. Does
anyone know?
Does anyone know? Put in chat. Anyone
know what the high ethnic group with the
highest rate of diabetes?
I bet you you guys don't know. Or maybe
someone knows. Maybe someone knows.
Does anyone know?
Well, I'll just tell you
the ethnic group with the highest rate
of diabetes
is the Puma Indians.
Mostly from um I think Arizona area.
Nope, not black you guys. Not Spanish.
see Pima Indians. But guess what? The
Puma Indians were a larger group
like 700 years ago, I think, a long time
ago. And they split. And some of them
settled in northern Mexico. Some of them
settled not Pacific Islander Native
Americans, but certain Native Americans,
Puma Indians in particular. Um, like I
said, they split. Some of them uh
settled in northern Mexico. Some of them
settled in southern part of the United
States, southwest.
So the Pima Indians have very close
relatives, if you will, in northern
Mexico. It turns out that their close
relatives in northern Mexico,
live in a northern state of Mexico
called Chihuahua.
They live in the Sierras of Chihuahua.
And they're actually famous. You know
why? Because they run. They're runners.
Not only do they run, they run long uh
races, like 100 mile races, and they
usually come up in the top 10.
They're famous for that. And they're
called the Tada Indians. I don't know
how many of you have heard of them.
They
like to run in their, you know, very
traditional
uh robes or whatever their their dress,
their uh attire and their even their
shoes are like sandals. They run in
those sandals. And like I said, they run
even 100 mile races. They usually are in
the top 10, even top five. They eat a
very simple diet, mostly plant-based.
They're very, uh, humble means. They
don't have a lot of money. They don't
have, you know, uh, McDonald's up in the
Sierras. They don't have Burger Kings
or, you know, Taco Bells or any of that.
They they grow their own food. They eat
corn, beans, you know, their own greens,
things they grow. They eat meat maybe a
few times a year whenever they have like
a big party, you know, a couple times a
year. Uh even the women run. In fact,
you can even go to Netflix and they
watch a documentary called Lorena.
Lorena and it talks about a girl that
runs. It's pretty cool. So anyway, what
I want to say is that uh the Puma or the
Pima Indians and the Taramada are like
closely related genetically. They're
like first cousins practically. They
have almost the same genes. And the
taradas have some of the lowest rates of
diabetes in the world.
In the world. They have almost the same
genes as the Puma Indians. And the Puma
Indians have the highest rates of
diabetes in the United States. The
taradas have the lowest one of the
lowest rates of diabetes in the world.
So is it the genes? That's the main
point. Is it the jeans?
No, it's not the jeans.
You can turn off the jeans or turn them
on. It's up to you. The lifestyle is
what turns the jeans on or off. It's up
to you. So, I just want to finish saying
that diabetes is one of the things that
will age your body the fastest. it
that blood sugar goes all over the body
and does damage everywhere like we said
before and your your risk for heart
attack your diet is part of it for sure.
Um your risk for heart attack like we
said goes up incredibly just with
pre-diabetes 50%. But with diabetes up
to 400%.
uh because like we said and and your
risk for stroke goes up incredibly
because even the arteries of your um
brain start to be affected as I said
before 70% of diabetics die of either a
heart attack or a stroke and of course
we have all these other complications
like I mentioned before renal failure
and we have vision problems blindness
and uh amputations because the
infections because they're
immune system is quite lowered.
All this blood sugar higher lowers the
immune system. That's a that's a whole
other topic. When CO came up, that's
when my videos went viral because I
started talking about the uh immune
system. The immune system and how to
improve your immune system following
eight basic principles. Poof. My videos
went really viral with that. So anyway,
the four the fourpart series we're going
to delve very deeply into how completely
reverse
pre-diabetes and the underlying
condition for pre-diabetes and type two
diabetes which is actually insulin
resistance and uh you know people
sometimes say well type two diabetes is
not curable. In fact, when I went to
teach one time a a class, it's one of
the first classes I taught at the clinic
I used to work. The doctor who actually
sent me some of her patients,
she went with me to teach one of the
classes and one of the first things she
said to the patients is like, "If you're
all diabetics, let me tell you that
diabetes, you will have it for the rest
of your life. You diabetes cannot be
cured." And I was like, "Oh no, why did
she say this?" is I was going to tell
them that actually it could be because
guess what well I did tell them the next
time the next class I said you know
there's new research that a lot of
doctors haven't even heard about it's
brand new you know I tried to out of
respect for the doctor to not contradict
her but
it is true a lot of doctors haven't even
heard of this this is a consensus
statement from the ADA the American
Diabetes Association
And do you see the title? How do we
define cure? I didn't say it. American
Diabetes Association.
I didn't say it.
They're talking about well, they say
remission later in the paper. But
whatever. You can call it cure,
remission, whatever you want. Reversal.
The point is you can lower your blood
sugar to the point of not qualifying as
diabetic anymore in about 85 to 90% of
the cases. Maybe not everyone. There's
some cases where after years and years
and years of diabetic of diabetes and
over producing insulin it is possible
that the pancreas can be uh
you know it could be exhausted. It can
be used up too much. It cannot function
any any more properly and it could be
that a person cannot possibly reverse it
100% after many years of being diabetic.
But it is possible that in most cases it
could possibly be reversed. So who am I
to say? It could be reversed. But for
that you need to go to the root cause.
So just taking medication it only covers
the symptom. The symptom is high blood
sugar. You need to go to the root cause
and that's is the insulin resistance. Uh
so it could be done. I just wanted to
show you some papers that talk about it
could be done in a sustainable manner.
Uh this is New Start from Weimar.
They've done it for 40 years. You can
read books about it. These are some of
the books that talk about it. Dr. Jill
Ferman, Dr. Neil Barnard has done it.
There's many many books you can read.
And of course, there's books from other
authors that talk about the other
complications like heart disease.
There's books about that talk about the
um autoimmune diseases and many um many
other things that uh that you can you
know like documentaries and stuff. So
why isn't is this more widely known?
Well, because first of all it takes
sometimes decades, generations for this
information to trickle down from
research into medical practice.
Sometimes the doctors
just think that the the patients won't
follow it unfortunately and sometimes
it's true the patients won't follow it.
They rather take the pill. Sometimes we
as patients want to want the easy way
out. They we as patients sometimes
rather take the pill. So sometimes
doctors are right. Sometimes the doctors
just think or
they just don't have the time. Honestly,
they have 10 minutes. I used to work in
a clinical setting and I I used to see
how pressured doctors are to hurry up
and see more patients. You know, it
depends on the setting, but sometimes
doctors themselves are pressured for
productivity. They need to see so many
patients a day. they just don't have the
time to sit down and talk with each
patient for one hour to tell them about
the diet and the exercise and all. They
just don't have that kind of time. So,
it's just easier to write a prescription
and just next, you know, unfortunately,
it's just the reality. And um in medical
journals, this is another truth. Very
sad, but they're dominated by the
pharmaceutical industry that sponsors
the studies. So not all these studies
are published in the more you know uh
the more
read out p you know the studies that are
the the journals that are more widely
read. That's just the sad reality
unfortunately.
So that's why a lot of doctors don't
know. It's just not as well known.
Anyway, we're trying to make it more
well known.
The next class, the next session in two
weeks, we're going to go very in detail
about the best diet to reverse
insulin resistance, which is related to
all those other complications that we
talked about, pre-diabetes and type two
diabetes.
So if you want to know all the details
about what's the best diet, so the
actual
eating pattern,
nutrition for insulin resistance,
remember it's related to all those
metabolic conditions,
pre-diabetes and diabetes,
it will be in two weeks. Okay, we're
going to talk about just the diet. After
that, we're going to talk about the best
kind of exercise. And most people have
no idea. They just think walk. No, it's
so much it's so much more than that.
People are just mistaken about just
there's mo so much more to that. Okay.
So, we're going to talk about that in
four weeks. And then we're going to talk
about other things that much more that
people have no idea about. There's just
so much more I want to share with you.
But anyway,
with this is just the introduction. Uh
there's more so much more information. I
just wanted to show you one thing
though. Uh in the the uh program that we
do at my work, I just told you community
RX aluden to plateau. I wanted to show
you just the results of our first year.
Um these are just the averages of our
first year. We've done it for two years
uh now and um and it's just about the
same. But I just wanted to show you the
averages. Again, we don't go to people's
houses. We don't control what they eat,
but we give them suggestions. And this
is more or less what we've seen in just
10 days. We see that the best results is
definitely for lipids because we ask
them to eat no uh oil. And so just
leaving out the oil, leaving out the uh
animal products, the lipids go down
quite dramatically. So you can see right
there the total the total cholesterol is
14% drop, but the LDL is 22% drop. So
that's very very dramatic. That's what
you really uh can drop without oil and
no animal products. The triglycerides go
down pretty good 6% and the glucose goes
down about 5%.
So that's just in two or 10 days. But
what we have seen
in uh in about three months like in uh
new start program is that if people
follow this for three months and they
add so this is just the diet. If you add
the lifestyle
uh habits like exercise, sleep and um
and all the other things like stress
management and all the drinking water,
all the lifestyle changes. If you add
incorporate all of it by about 3 months
over 80% of people who follow all the
exercise and all the lifestyle habits
including the diet about 80% of
diabetics can reverse the diabetes if
they do it. So I think that's great. I
don't know about you but I think that's
wonderful. Okay, I want to leave you my
website once again healthfortoday.net.
net because if any of you guys haven't
gone there and you want to try eating a
plantbased diet for 10 days, you can try
it. If you haven't done it yet, I
recommend you do it. You can download
the 10day program, the Daniel Challenge,
from this website, healthfortoday.net.
And so if you go there,
you see right there on the top it says
um what does it say? 10day challenge.
10day challenge. You click there and
it's free. You don't even have to leave
me your your you know sometimes you go
to these websites and you have to leave
your email or whatever. I don't even ask
you to do that. Just just download it.
Um, you can also do the intermittent
fasting. And if you combine a
plant-based diet and intermittent
fasting,
I don't think how you cannot not lose
weight. For people who want to lose
weight, I think it's almost impossible
not to lose weight if you combine those
two things. So, anyway, I think I've uh
gone over my time as I usually do. If
you have any questions, I can answer any
leftover questions unless the producer
says no, you have to go now. Um, but I
wanted to thank you for
for your time. I hope this has questions
are fine. She said questions is fine. If
you guys have any questions, let me know
or else we'll finish with prayer. But I
wanted to thank you for your time and I
hope this has been beneficial to you.
Uh, let's see. Ah, perfect. Uh, I hope
this has been beneficial for you. I hope
this has given you at least an idea of
what uh we will be talking next. So,
next in two weeks from Thank you. You're
welcome, Candy. Thank you. Thank you for
for connecting. Thank you for being with
us. Um, I am very excited. I hope that
the next few presentations
will be beneficial. I I hope you invite
people to connect the next three
sessions because it will be a complete
seminar on reversal of diabetes and
pre-diabetes and insulin resistance and
all the metabolic conditions that are
related to insulin resistance. So
hypertension,
hyper lipidmia that means high
cholesterol, LDL cholesterol which is
the bad cholesterol or high
triglycerides,
fatty liver,
that's another one that's very much a
metabolic condition. Of course, anybody
who has um high overweight or obesity
usually it has to do with metabolic
condition because anyone who has high uh
or insulin resistance producing too much
um too much insulin and insulin itself
is a growth hormone and therefore it
makes you got weight g uh gain weight.
So it is very hard to lose weight if you
have hyperinsulinemia.
So, anybody who has overweight, obesity,
high uh cholesterol, high triglycerides,
hypertension, any of these things,
try to make them watch this one and the
next three. If I am oil free, can I
still have avocados? I absolutely
recommend eating avocados,
nuts, seeds,
any of these healthy fats, especially
with your salads.
Not a lot. You don't want to eat two,
three, four avocados a day. U a handful
of nuts is about one ounce is just about
right for most people. Unless you are a
very active person like an athlete,
maybe two handfuls or you know someone
who is pregnant might need more
calories. Uh but you want to actually
add those healthy fats especially to
your salads. Why? Because the those
antioxidants like the beta carotens for
instance, these are fat soluble. So if
you're not adding fats to your salads,
healthy fats with the fiber, nuts, you
could be like you can make a dressing
for instance with cashews or walnuts or
almonds or avocado or just add the
avocados, chop them up, put them on top.
any of these things uh or put you know
like flax seeds any of these things any
healthy fats will help you absorb the uh
beta carotene and any of these other um
any of these other very healthy
antioxidants that are in the salads and
in in the veggies. So yes, I absolutely
recommend eating a healthy amount of fat
every day. About 1 ounce of nuts or
seeds or, you know, maybe about 50 grams
of avocados. So maybe an ounce and a
half or something. Depends if you want
to lose weight or if you're trying to
gain weight. So it depends on each
person.
I restarted my vegetarian eating. I plan
uh plans starting last Friday. Awesome,
Harriet. Congrats. Congratulations.
Are there any recommended apps? I'm glad
you asked. Actually, I do have a friend
who is a Food for Life instructor and
Food for Life is a program with PCRM,
Physicians Committee for Responsible
Medicine. And they have an app called
21day Vegan. I don't work for them. I
just know that my friend is an
instructor. So, it's called 21
21 Vegan Kickstart, and it's an app. Uh,
most of the recipes are pretty good. I
like them. They're at least plant-based.
You can even do grocery shopping lists
and all these things. They have plenty
of recipes. You can even change it to
Spanish in the settings if you want
Spanish recipes in Spanish. Uh, so
anyway, it's pretty good app, so I'm
glad you asked. Awesome. Any other
questions? If you're going to have any
other questions, I think we will finish
with prayer. And so, um, let's not
forget that our next, uh, our next
program will be July 8th. And it 21day
vegan kickstart. That's the one. So, I
think it will be a good one. It will be
a good one, you guys. Tons of recipes.
You can even do a shopping list. It's
great. It's pretty good. Just if if
there's any, you know, I don't think
there's any oil, but if there's any oil,
just you can leave it out or whatever.
Um, it's up to you. All right. July 8th,
don't forget the diet.
Share it with your friends. Okay, let's
let's finish with a prayer.
Dear heavenly father, thank you so much
for today. Thank you for the opportunity
to do this program. Thank you for all
the knowledge you have given us and
given access to us that we can share
with other people. Help us, Lord, to
share this with this information with
others that might need it. And um help
us to be your ambassadors wherever we go
that we may help others to know you
better um and to
help them to know that you are our
healer and our savior. In Jesus name we
pray. Amen. Thank you once again. See
you in two weeks. Thank you for being
with us. God bless you and good night.
Thank you. Thank you everyone. Thank you
Deborah. Thank you Harriet.
And thank you Matina.
And let's see who else. Mountains and
the Sea. Candy
YBJ. Thank you everyone. Good night.